Finding Aid for Vice-President for Development (University of Michigan) records, 1948-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vice-President for Development (University of Michigan) records
1948-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development.
Records of University of Michigan office (and its predecessor administrative offices) responsible for external fund raising and development activities, including subject files of development officials Arthur Brandon, Lyle Nelson, and Michael Radock; staff files; and photographs.
87366 Bimu B6 2
54 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The material was received from the vice-president's office (Donor No. 3813 ) in June 1982, May 1984, and in periodic accessions thereafter.
The collection is open for research.
The office now designated the Vice President for Development has undergone a number of changes in title and responsibilities since its inception. While today it is a fundraising unit, the office from which this unit evolved was established as a vehicle for communicating information about the university to those outside.
As early as 1897 the regents of the University of Michigan recognized the need for a means through which official information about the university could be issued. Rather than establish a separate organization, the regents chose to graft this responsibility onto existing university units, offering a small sum of money to these units to cover additional expenses. Between 1897 and 1942 the department of rhetoric (1897-1901, 1912-1928), the Alumni Association (1901-1912), and the Bureau of Alumni Relations carried out this task. The work of the Bureau of Alumni Relations fell under the broad mandate of James B. Bruce, who in 1931 became the first university officer to bear the title Vice President in charge of University Relations. Bruce, a doctor by training, was an influential member of the Medical School faculty and held several important positions simultaneously. Bruce's general mandate was to oversee all university contacts with the non-academic world, most importantly by monitoring the intellectual content of post-graduate courses and presentations. Bruce personally seems to have had little interest in public relations.
At the time of Bruce's retirement in 1942 the regents decided that the responsibility for disseminating information from the university should be placed in a distinct unit, reporting to the university's central administration. As a result, the University News Service was founded. In 1944, when Marvin L. Niehuss assumed Bruce's title, he also assumed indirect responsibility for the two-year-old News Service. Niehuss, however, shared Bruce's lack of interest in public relations. A member of the Law School faculty, he was asked by the president to concentrate upon the relationship between the university and the state legislature.
Recognizing the need for a person with skills in public relations, the regents in 1945 agreed in principle to hire a full-time senior administrator to handle the university's relations with the public. In 1946 Arthur L. Brandon was hired to fill this position and was given the title Director of Information Services. Brandon's graduate training had been in the field of public relations and he had worked at various universities, including Vanderbilt and the University of Texas, in positions similar to this one. Brandon undertook an ambitious program to reach the various publics the university serves. He established, or re-established, several publications and offered public relations expertise to the entire campus community. He was also interested in the electronic media. Under Brandon the university began to broadcast over two wholly-owned radio stations, superseding the former practice of irregularly broadcasting programs over commercial radio stations. In 1950 Brandon began to experiment with educational television. He aggressively promoted Michigan productions and by the middle of the decade the university had more program outlets than any other educational institution.
Brandon was also an innovator in fundraising. After World War II the university initiated the Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project. Intended as a memorial to former University of Michigan students who had died in World War II, the campaign raised money to support research on the peaceful uses of atomic energy. Unlike similar efforts in the past, however, after the immediate goals of the Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project were achieved, the staff responsible for fundraising was not dismissed. Instead, in 1951 the staff was placed under Brandon's purview. In 1953 ongoing fundraising was given a formal organization through the Development Council. The University of Michigan was the first public institution to establish a permanent fundraising unit.
In 1951, as part of a general reorganization of the university, Brandon was given a new title, Director of University Relations, and reported directly to the president. Brandon held this title for six years, resigning it in 1957 to accept a vice presidency at New York University. Lyle M. Nelson, a professor of journalism, replaced Brandon. Nelson had served previously as an assistant to President Harlan Hatcher (1953-55) before leaving Ann Arbor to go to San Francisco State College. After his return to the University of Michigan, Nelson continued the policies of his predecessor in the areas of public relations and fundraising. The growing responsibilities of the office led to the designation of Nelson as Vice President for University Relations in 1960. The Presidents Club, a widely-imitated fundraising mechanism, was founded in 1961 during Nelson's tenure; designed to attract large private gifts to the university, the club required a contribution of $10,000 for membership.
Nelson was succeeded in 1961 by Michael Radock. Formerly a professor of journalism at Kent State University, Radock came to the University of Michigan from Ford Motor Company, where he had been a member of the corporate public relations staff and manager of education affairs. Radock continued the substantive public information programs of his predecessors and also continued their tradition of innovative fundraising approaches.
In 1964 Michael Radock oversaw the $55 Million Campaign, which broke new ground for public institutions. Traditionally institutions had sought private funds for a specific project. In the late 1950s, however, Harvard revolutionized fundraising techniques by holding the first modern capital campaign. Rather than seeking support for a single project, Harvard asked its alumni and friends to support the general good of the institution, listing as the campaign's goals a group of needed capital improvements as well as support for endowment funds. Michigan was the first public institution to adopt a similar fundraising approach. In the course of this campaign the staff of the Development Office, which until then had worked almost exclusively with the Development Council, came more directly under the jurisdiction of the vice president.
In the late 1970s Radock launched another major fundraising initiative through the authorization of a systematic and comprehensive census of alumni. The project's goal was to locate all living university alumni, making possible regular contact with them which would, it was hoped, lead to an increased percentage of alumni making annual contributions to the university.
Between 1961 and 1981, when Radock retired, he exercised his authority under a series of titles. When first hired he was designated Director of University Relations. In 1964 he was given his predecessor's title, Vice President for University Relations. In 1969 he was named Vice President for University Relations and Development.
When Jon Cosovich assumed the office in 1983 his title was Vice President for Development and University Relations. This was changed in 1985 to Vice President for Development and Communication. The shift away from communication toward fundraising was complete in 1988, when responsibility for communication with the larger community was transferred to the newly-created Office of University Relations and Cosovich's title became simply Vice President for Development.
Senior University Information Officer and Fundraiser
1931-1942 James B. Bruce, Vice-President in charge of University Relations
1944-1951 Marvin L. Niehuss, Vice President in charge of University Relations
1946-1957 Arthur L. Brandon, Director of Information Services
1951-1957 Arthur L. Brandon, Director of University Relations
1957-1960 Lyle M. Nelson, Director of University Relations
1960-1961 Lyle M. Nelson, Vice President for University Relations
1961-1964 Michael Radock, Director of University
1964-1969 Michael Radock, Vice President for University Relations
1969-1981 Michael Radock, Vice President for University Relations and Development
1981-1983 Harvey K. Jacobson, Acting Vice President for University Relations and Development
1983-1985 Jon Cosovich, Vice President for Development and University Relations
1985-1988 Jon Cosovich, Vice President for Development and Communication
1988-1994 Jon Cosovich, Vice President for Development
1988-1994 Thomas C. Kinnear, Vice President for Development
Vice Presidents subgroup Arthur Brandon/Lyle Nelson, 1953-1959 [Boxes 1-4] Lyle Nelson/Michael Radock, 1959-1962 [Boxes 4-6] Michael Radock 1960-1964 (primarily 1962-1963) [Box 7] 1963-1980 (primarily 1964-1976) [Boxes 7-10] 1973-1983 (primarily 1977-1981) External correspondence [Boxes 10-11] Internal correspondence [Box 11] Unit correspondence [Box 11] Senior staff meeting minutes [Boxes 11-12] Reorganization plans [Box 12] Round-Up [Box 12] Jon Cosovich, 1981-1996 [Boxes 39-43]
Development Office subgroup Foundation Relations Chronological (1976-1980) [box 13] Committees [box 13] Conferences [box 13] Projects (funding for) [box 13] Schools and Colleges files [boxes 13-16] Topical file Historical files, 1948-1977 [box 16] Alphabetical file [boxes 17-22] Visual Material Photographs [box 23] Slides [box33-38 Videotape [box 38] Staff Files Annual Funds Coordinating Council [boxes 24-26] Annual Giving Program [boxes 26-28] Capital Campaigns Campaign for Michigan [boxes 28-29] Cultural Programs/friends groups [boxes 29-30] Development Council [box 30] Tappan Hall fundraising [boxes 30-31] Topical file [boxes 31-32] Capital Campaigns, 1964-1994 [boxes 43-44] Committees, 1980-1998 [boxes 44-47] Topical Files, 1960-1997 [boxes 47-48] Artifacts [box 49]
The records of the Vice President for Development date from 1948 to the present and measure 39.5 linear feet. They reflect the basic concerns of the office for these four decades: preserving and improving the university's public image and planning major fundraising efforts. Unfortunately, both activities are incompletely documented. In the area of public relations the records tend to discuss how immediate problems will be dealt with, rather than overall conceptions of the university's image. The thought behind the innovative fundraising devices created or employed by the office is sometimes recorded through consultant reports, but in general is not well documented.
The manuscript records have been divided into two subgroups, one representing the records of the vice president (or senior staff person, for those years in which there was no vice presidency), the other containing records created by the development office. The Vice Presidents subgroup has been divided by the name of each person who has held the office: Arthur Brandon, Lyle Nelson, and Michael Radock. Researchers should note that since Nelson and Radock used their predecessor's files for some time before inaugurating their own records, the relationship between office tenure and file dates is not an exact one. The Development Office subgroup contains records of that office and its subsidiary units. Several accessions of Development Office records received in 1989 and 1990 have been grouped together as Development Office subgroup: 1989-1990 accessions.
Subjects:
American College Public Relations Association.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Council for Advancement and Support of Education.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; Sigma Nu. Gamma Nu chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Administration.Administration.; University of Michigan. Broadcasting Service.; University of Michigan. Development Council.; University of Michigan. Foundations Relations Office.; University of Michigan--Finance.Finance.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.StudentsSocieties, etc.; University of Michigan--Gifts and loans.Gifts and loans.; University of Michigan--Students--Political activity.StudentsPolitical activity.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development and Communication.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development and University Relations.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Educational fund raising--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Inglis House (University of Michigan); Interlochen Center for the Arts.; Laboratories.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.Campus.; University of Michigan--Commencements.Commencements.; University of Michigan--Football.Football.; University of Michigan--Research.Research.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.StudentsSocial life and customs1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.StudentsSocial life and customs1981-1990.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development and Communication.; University of Michigan--Student housing.Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Nelson, Lyle Morgan, 1918-; Radock, Michael, 1917-; Brandon, Arthur Leon.
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Vice Presidents
  - Arthur Brandon/Lyle Nelson, 1953-1959
    - A (Box 1)
    - Academic calendar, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Officers, Memos to (Box 1)
    - Alumni Development Council, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - American Association of University Professors (AAUP). (Box 1)
      (See University Professor, American Association of)
    - Annual reports, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor, City of (Box 1)
    - Band scholarships (Box 1)
    - Big Ten budget requests (Box 1)
    - Brandon, Arthur L
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box 1)
    - Dearborn Center (Box 1)
    - Development Council
      - Alumni Fund, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
      - Budget (Box 1)
      - General correspondence (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Newsletter (Box 1)
      - Report to President (Box 1)
      - Survey of needs (Box 1)
    - Engineering, College of (Box 1)
    - Financial Aid to Education (Box 1)
    - Football (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - G (Box 1)
    - Hospital, University--public relations (Box 1)
    - House Un-American Activities Committee. (Box 1)
      See: Un-American Activities Committee
    - Human Resources Program
      - General, 1958 (Box 1)
      - Research (Box 1)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 1)
      [See: Social Research, Institute for]
    - Institute of Science and Technology (Box 1)
      See: Science and Technology, Institute of
    - Investment Program for Michigan Endowment Funds (Box 1)
    - Law School (Box 2)
    - Lecture Committee (Box 2)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of (Box 2)
    - M (Box 2)
    - Mount Sinai Expedition (Box 2)
    - N (Box 2)
    - O (Box 2)
    - P (Box 2)
    - Phoenix Project
      - Board of Governors (Box 2)
      - Campaign Committee (Box 2)
      - Continuation Project (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Ford Foundation Presentation (Box 2)
      - Literature (Box 2)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
      - Public Relations Advisory Committee (Box 2)
      - Publicity (Box 2)
      - Steering Committee (Box 2)
    - Physical Education for Women (Box 2)
      [See: Women's Physical Education]
    - Pierpont, Wilbur K (Box 2)
    - Public relations (Box 2)
    - R (Box 2)
    - Radio
      - Flint and Grand Rapids stations (Box 2)
      - Personnel (Box 2)
    - Rand Corporation (Box 2)
    - Regents (Box 2)
    - Requests--general (Box 2)
    - Residence Halls (Box 2)
    - Russell Study Commission on Higher Education, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - S (Box 2)
    - Science--general (Box 3)
    - Science and Technology, Institute of (Box 3)
    - Social Research, Institute for (Box 3)
    - Soul, Dr. Malcolm (Box 3)
    - Speeches--miscellaneous, 1952-1958 (Box 3)
    - Stirton, W.E (Box 3)
    - Student Affairs (Box 3)
    - Student Government Council (Box 3)
    - Student Publications (Box 3)
    - T (Box 3)
    - Television
      - Channel 12 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence--general (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Television and Radio Broadcasting Committee
      - Actions (Box 3)
      - Correspondence--general (Box 3)
      - Policies (Box 3)
    - Television Studio--plans and equipment (Box 3)
    - Triad Television Corporation (Box 3)
    - U (Box 3)
    - Un-American Activity Committee Hearings, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - University budget
      - State legislation
        - 1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - 1959 (Box 4)
    - University movies (Box 4)
    - University News Service (Box 4)
    - University Press (Box 4)
    - University Press Club of Michigan (Box 4)
    - University Professors, American Association of (Box 4)
    - University Relations--Community Services (Box 4)
    - V-W (Box 4)
    - Williams, Robert L (Box 4)
    - Willow Run Airport
      - General correspondence (Box 4)
      - Research
        - Engineering (Box 4)
        - "Wolverine" Engineering Research (Box 4)
    - Women's Physical Education (Box 4)
    - WUOM (Box 4)
    - X-Y-Z (Box 4)
    - Young Adult Council (Box 4)
  - Lyle Nelson/Michael Radock, 1957-1962
    The Lyle Nelson/Michael Radock series contains records created between 1959 and 1964. It is identical in structure to the Brandon/Nelson series and is most notable for its information about the trip to the Soviet Union made by Harlan Hatcher in 1959. Nelson accompanied Hatcher to Russia and retained a great deal of information about the visit.
    - A (Box 4)
    - Alumni Association-University of Michigan correspondence
      - 1960 (Box 4)
      - 1961 (Box 4)
    - Alumni clubs--general correspondence (Box 4)
    - American Alumni Council (Box 4)
    - American Association of University Professors (Box 4)
    - Art Center (proposed) (Box 4)
    - Athletics, Board in Control of Intercollegiate (Box 4)
    - Athletics--general correspondence (Box 5)
    - Athletics--Intercollegiate Conference (Box 5)
    - B (Box 5)
    - Bands--spring tour reports
      - 1962 (Box 5)
      - 1963 (Box 5)
      - 1964 (Box 5)
    - Band, University of Michigan
      - General (Box 5)
      - Russian Tour, 1961; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Beeuwkes, Adelia (Box 5)
    - Big Ten Group (Box 5)
    - Big Ten Committee on Institutional Cooperation (Box 5)
    - Board in Control of Student Publications (Box 5)
    - C (Box 5)
    - California, University of (Box 5)
    - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (Box 5)
      [See: Big Ten Committee on Institutional Cooperation]
    - Committee on Unified Planning (UM-WSU) (Box 5)
    - Compliment letters, 1958-1960 (Box 5)
    - Cross, Robert (Box 5)
    - D (Box 5)
    - Fluoridation (Box 5)
      [See: Beeuwkes, Adelia]
    - Ford Foundation (Box 5)
    - Ford Motor Company (Box 5)
    - G (Box 5)
    - Government of Michigan (Box 5)
    - H (Box 5)
    - Higher Education in Michigan, 1960 (Box 5)
    - I (Box 5)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 5)
    - Institute of Science and Technology (Box 5)
    - International Development, Conference on (Box 5)
    - J (Box 5)
    - Joint Office of Institute Research--Land Grant College (Box 5)
    - K (Box 6)
    - Legislative--miscellaneous correspondence (Box 6)
    - M (Box 6)
    - Michigan State University (Box 6)
    - N (Box 6)
    - National Defense Association (Box 6)
    - Niehuss, Marvin L (Box 6)
    - P (Box 6)
    - Pierpont, Wilbur K (Box 6)
    - President's Reports (Box 6)
    - Professional Theater
      - 1960 (Box 6)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 6)
    - Soviet Trip, 1959
      - Educational Delegation Visit (Box 6)
      - Syllabi (Box 6)
      - General files, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Suomalainen, Kari: visit of University of Michigan (Box 6)
    - Toynbee, Arnold (Box 6)
    - United Negro College Fund (Box 6)
    - University Press Club of Michigan, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Michael Radock, 1960-1983
    The Michael Radock series (1960-1983) is the most complex in arrangement. The Radock series has three chronological divisions: 1960-1964 (primarily 1962-1963), 1963-1980 (primarily 1964-1976), and 1973-1983 (primarily 1977-1981). The first two divisions are arranged alphabetically by topic, as were the previous files. The first, 1960-1964, is very small, and is of interest primarily for information on the Sigma Nu controversy. Sigma Nu was a local fraternity that came under fire in Ann Arbor because of a provision in the organization's national charter banning Blacks from membership.
    The second, 1963-1980, is of interest in terms of the $55 Million Campaign (the last heading in the series), the Black Action Movement (BAM) and the BAM strike, and radio stations WUOM and WCBN. There is also incomplete information about protests regarding the appearance of George Lincoln Rockwell, leader of the American Nazi Party, at the University of Michigan in 1964. Beyond the campus, Radock was an active participant in professional organizations, particularly the American College Public Relations Association (ACPRA), of which he was president. This series contains extensive information about ACPRA and about its merger with the American Alumni Council, which resulted in the formation of the Council for the Advancement and Support of Education (CASE).
    - 1960-1964
      - A-C (Box 7)
      - Arms control symposium (Box 7)
      - Board in Control of Student Publications. (Box 7)
        (See: Student Publications, Board in Control of)
      - Constitutional Convention (Box 7)
      - D-F (Box 7)
      - Delta College (Box 7)
      - Economic Development Committee (Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce)
        - Correspondence (Box 7)
        - Membership (Box 7)
        - Minutes, 1963 (Box 7)
      - H-J (Box 7)
      - International Education, Institute of (Box 7)
      - K-M (Box 7)
      - N-R (Box 7)
      - NASA Electronics Research Center Proposal
        - Proposal (Box 7)
        - Scrapbook, 1963-1964 (Box 7)
      - S (Box 7)
      - Sawyer, Ralph A (Box 7)
      - Sigma Nu (racial controversy) (Box 7)
      - Soviet Union (Box 7)
      - Student Publications, Board in Control of (Box 7)
      - U (Box 7)
      - University of Michigan Commentary (Box 7)
      - W (Box 7)
      - Water Pollution Laboratory (Box 7)
    - 1963-1980
      (primarily 1964-1976)
      - Affirmative Action Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
      - Allstate visit, 1975 (Box 7)
      - Alumni Center--permanent, 1972-1977 (Box 7)
      - Alumni Development Information System--summary, 1976 (Box 7)
      - American College Public Relations Association (ACPRA)
        - Awards judging, 1977 (Box 7)
        - Board of Trustees, 1966-1970 (Box 7)
        - College and University Journal, 1968 (Box 7)
        - Committees
          - Executive
            - 1966-1969 (Box 8)